Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Charles J. Balestrino Papers, 1986-1994 and undated RL.00663
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Charles J. Balestrino papers
1986-1994 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
RL.00663
6 Linear Feet
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Charles J. Balestrino was an executive, primarily in account management, at JWT offices in New York, Detroit, San Francisco and Tokyo. The JWT Charles J. Balestrino Papers span the years 1986-1994 and include correspondence, presentations, photographs, and videocassettes that document the later years of Balestrino's career at JWT's New York Office. Correspondents include Burt Manning, John Furr and Bill Thompson. Clients represented in the collection include Esso/Exxon, Goodyear, IBM, and Northwest Airlines. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
4200 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Charles J. Balestrino Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 1994.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1941 Dec. 3 Born, New York
1963 BS, Business/Psychology, C.W. Post College
1964-1968 U.S. Marine Corps, discharged with rank of Captain
1968-1969 Assistant Account Executive, Grey Advertising
1969-1970 Account Manager, JWT New York
1970-1974 Account Supervisor, JWT New York
1974-1978 Vice President and Management Supervisor, JWT New York
1978-1983 Senior Vice President, JWT Detroit
1983-1985 Senior Vice President, JWT San Francisco
1984 Elected to JWT Board of Directors
1985-1986 Senior Vice President, JWT Tokyo
1986 Management Director, Ford Division account, JWT Detroit
1987-1991 Executive Vice President and General Manager, JWT Detroit
1991-1994 Executive Vice President and Director, JWT New York
Collection Overview
The JWT Charles J. Balestrino Papers span the years 1986-1994 and include correspondence, presentations, photographs, and videocassettes that document the later years of Balestrino's career at JWT's New York Office. Correspondents include Burt Manning, John Furr and Bill Thompson. Clients represented in the collection include Esso/Exxon, Goodyear, IBM, and Northwest Airlines.
Collection Arrangement
Arranged into the following series: Account Files, Office Files, Personal Files and Audiovisual Materials. Original folder titles have been maintained where possible. Arranged alphabetically.
Conditions Governing Access note
Restrictions on Access: Original audiovisual materials are closed to researchers until a use copy can be produced.
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections of the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives:
Account Files
Iconographic Collection
New Business Records
Edgar Hatcher Papers
Jack Peters Papers
Photographs; Videocassettes; Advertising executives; Advertising executives -- United States; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Advertising agencies; Northwest Airlines Corporation; Manning, Burt; Goodyear Tire and Rubber Company; International Business Machines Corporation; Balestrino, Charles J., 1941-; Exxon Company U.S.A.; J. Walter Thompson Company; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office; J. Walter Thompson Company
- Account Files, 1989-1993 and undated, 5 boxes
  - DeBeers
    - Marketing the Gift of Love Around the World, undated (Box 1)
  - Esso/Exxon
    - 1992 Action Plan in Mexico, 1992 June (Box 1)
    - 1993/1994 Advertising Campaign proposal, 1992 Oct., 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Account objective, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Advertising assessment, 1992 Aug. (Box 1)
    - Analysis of brand image, undated (Box 1)
    - Assessment of branding options, 1992 Oct. (Box 1)
    - Creative assessment and storyboards, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Evaluation report, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Exxon account plan, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Exxon forecourt design evaluation, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Implications for the brand, 1991 Oct. (Box 1)
    - International Account Directors Conference, 1993 Mar. (Box 1)
    - International account history, undated (Box 1)
    - International competitive review, 1992 July (Box 1)
    - Latin America, 1992 Nov. (Box 1)
    - Presentation: The Building of a Multi-National Account, 1992 Sept. (Box 1)
    - Presentation to CJB (Chile), 1993 (Box 1)
    - Changing Gears with Esso, undated (Box 2)
    - Presentation to Europe Advertising Managers, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Presentation to K. Fink, 1992 Aug. (Box 2)
    - Presentation: Lessons Learned, 1993 Apr. (Box 2)
    - Presentation: Moving to International Brand Management, 1992 Aug. (Box 2)
    - Presentation: The Value of an International Esso Positioning, undated (Box 2)
    - Report: Objectives of Today, undated (Box 2)
    - UK advertising development, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - UK TVCF Tiger Cub version, 1993 May (Box 2)
  - Goodyear
    - General, 1992 Jan. -1993 Feb. (Box 2)
    - 1992 launch plan, 1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 3-year business plan, 1991 Nov. (Box 2)
    - Asia/Pacific, 1992 Jan.-Aug. (Box 2)
    - Australia, 1992 Jan.-Feb. (Box 2)
    - Business Review Board meeting, 1992 Aug. (Box 2)
    - Canada, 1991-1993 (Box 3)
    - Client list, 1993 Nov. (Box 3)
    - Consumer studies, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - Las Vegas, Nev., Dealers' Conference, 1992 Jan. (Box 3)
    - Europe (JWT), 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - France, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Global village, 1991 (Box 3)
    - International, 1990-1993 (Box 3)
    - Jaguar presentation, 1992 Mar. (Box 3)
    - Latin America, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - Logo, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Market studies, 1989-1992, 1 of 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Market studies, 1989-1992 (continued), 2 of 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Media, 1992 May (Box 4)
    - Minority marketing, 1992 Nov. (Box 4)
    - Multinational client review, 1992 May (Box 4)
    - New Zealand, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Public relations, 1992 Feb. (Box 4)
    - Retail, 1990-1992 (Box 4)
    - South Africa, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - Tracking studies, 1992-1993, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Worldwide resources, undated (Box 4)
  - IBM
    - Account summary, 1992 July (Box 4)
    - Account status meeting and report, 1993 June (Box 4)
    - Preparatory information for Puckett meeting, 1993 Oct. (Box 4)
  - Northwest Airlines
    - Account status report, 1992 July (Box 4)
    - Brand advertising, 1992 June-July (Box 4)
    - Contract, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Chris Clouser, 1992 July (Box 5)
    - Financial reports, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Japan, 1992 July-Aug. (Box 5)
    - Memos/positions, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Multinational client review, 1992 May (Box 5)
    - Seabrook Marketing, 1992 July (Box 5)
    - TPAC, 1992 June-July (Box 5)
- Office Files, 1987-1994 and undated, 4 boxes
  - Administrative
    - Asia-Pacific operations, 1992 Jan. (Box 6)
    - Christmas card list (clients), 1991 (Box 6)
    - Christmas party (staff), 1990-1991 (Box 6)
    - Claim forms, 1991 (Box 6)
    - Contact information, undated (Box 6)
    - Detroit public relations, 1987-1989, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - D.I.C. meeting, 1993 July (Box 6)
    - D.I.C. presentation, 1993 Jan. (Box 6)
    - D.I.C. questionnaire, 1992-1993 (Box 6)
    - Flexible Spending reimbursement forms, undated (Box 6)
    - General Managers Meeting reports, 1989 Apr. (Box 6)
    - G.L.O.B.E. plans, 1993 (Box 6)
    - Notes to CJB, 1991, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Presentation: 1991 Worldwide Creative Review, 1992 July (Box 7)
    - Presentation: Advertising in the '90s, 1991 (Box 7)
    - Presentation: Enhancing the Effectiveness of Media Planning, undated (Box 7)
    - Presentation: Eveready, 1993 May (Box 7)
    - Presentation to Exxon Company, International, 1991 (Box 7)
    - Reader files, 1991, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Reader file index forms, 1990 (Box 7)
    - Resumes, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Speeches, 1992 (Box 7)
    - TMI, 1992 Mar. (Box 7)
    - Vacation/Personal days contracts, 1991 (Box 7)
    - Worldwide Creative Review: Selected competitors (1991), 1992 July (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    - CJB's Detroit chronological file, 1989-1991, 1 of 4 folders (Box 7)
    - CJB's Detroit chronological file, 1989-1991 (continued), 2-4 of 4 folders (Box 8)
    - CJB's letters, 1988 (Box 8)
    - CJB's meeting notices, 1988 (Box 8)
    - CJB'S memos, 1988, 1-2 of 9 folders (Box 8)
    - CJB'S memos, 1988 (continued), 3-9 of 9 folders (Box 9)
    - Esso memos, 1993-1994 (Box 10)
    - Goodyear memos, 1992-1993 (Box 10)
    - I.B.M. memos, 1993 (Box 10)
  - Individual Correspondence
    - Furr, John, 1993 (Box 10)
    - Thompson, Bill, 1993 (Box 10)
- Personal Files, 1988-1993, 1 box
  - Notes
    - Burt Manning's planners, 1993 (Box 10)
    - CJB's congratulatory file, 1988 (Box 10)
    - CJB's personal Christmas party, 1989 (Box 10)
    - Notes (miscellaneous), 1991 (Box 10)
  - Official Documents
    - Biographical sketch of CJB, 1986-1988 (Box 10)
    - CJB check requests, 1991, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Lawsuits, 1987-1989 (Box 10)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1 box
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Restrictions on access: Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
  - Goodyear Tire & Rubber Company commercials. 1992. Format: Umatic. TRT: 3:30 (Box 12)
    Scope and Contents note
    [Includes: Tires of the Future, Champions CART/GS, Champions NASCAR/GS, Choice Value, GA-A Intro/New Technology, The New Goodyear]